<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, at St. Margaret's Westminster, on the 30th of January, 1696/7 by William Lancaster ...</title>
            <author>Lancaster, William, 1650-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49241</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6275</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13088675</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13088675</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97331</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49241)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97331)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 744:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, at St. Margaret's Westminster, on the 30th of January, 1696/7 by William Lancaster ...</title>
                  <author>Lancaster, William, 1650-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Lamentations V, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:97331:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Lunae 1. die Feb. 1696.</date>
               </dateline> 
Ordered,</opener>
            <p>THat the Thanks of this Houſe be given to Doctor
<hi>Lancaſter,</hi> for the Sermon by him Preached before them, upon
<hi>Saturday</hi> laſt, at St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
And that he be deſired to Print the ſame, and that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Robert
Berty</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Drake</hi> do acquaint him therewith.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Paul Jodrell,</hi> Cl. Dom.
Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97331:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Before the Honourable Houſe of Commons, AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> On the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of
<hi>January,</hi> 1696/7.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM LANCASTER,</hi> D.D. Vicar of S. <hi>Martin</hi>'s
<hi>in the Fields.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the
<hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97331:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97331:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the Honourable Houſe of
Commons.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LAMENT. V. 16.</bibl> 
                  <p>The Crown is fallen from our Head; Wo to us, for we have
ſinned.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words are part of <hi>Jeremy</hi>'s Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and if we
look into 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.25. We ſhall find that this Lamentation was
for the Death of King <hi>Joſiah:</hi> The words of that place in
<hi>Chronicles</hi> are theſe, <hi>And</hi> Jeremiah <hi>lamented for</hi>
Joſiah, <hi>and all the ſinging men and ſinging women ſpake of</hi>
Joſiah <hi>in their lamentations to this day; and made them an Ordinance
in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and behold they are written in the Lamentations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe words, I conclude, That the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in this place,
ſpeaking of the downfall of the Crown, does it with relation to the Death of
that great and good King: The Chronicle<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97331:3"/>witneſſes, That
<hi>Jeremy</hi> made Lamentation for him, and that it was contain'd and
<hi>written in the Lamentations:</hi> And ſince theſe Words of the Prophet
do ſo well expreſs it, we muſt believe that <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s downfall
was the occaſion of them. He was a Pattern for all Princes, and the Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
which was to be in <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for him, was to be a
Pattern for all Lamentation.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Zechary,</hi> when he foretells the Paſſion
and dying of our Lord Jeſus upon the Croſs, ſays, There ſhall be ſuch
mourning for Him as was for <hi>Joſiah;</hi> That <hi>they ſhall look on
him whom they have pierced:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10.</note>
which S. <hi>John</hi> c. 19. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains and applies to our Saviour expoſed,
and wounded, and bleeding upon the Croſs. And then the Prophet adds,
<hi>v.</hi> 11. That <hi>in that day there ſhall be great mourning in
Jeruſalem, as the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the valley of Megiddon.</hi> The
La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation for our Lord, it is here foretold, ſhould be as great as that
for <hi>Joſiah,</hi> who was ſlain in the Field of Battle at
<hi>Megiddo;</hi> which ſeems to have been the greateſt Mourning that was
ever known in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words then I have ſufficiently explain'd by ſhewing the
occaſion of them: and the ſame Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory ſays, That hereupon an
<hi>Ordinance was made in Iſrael;</hi> and the Book which was written many
years, at leaſt ſome reigns after <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Death, ſays, the
obſervation of that Ordinance was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97331:3"/>a very long
time, <hi>They ſpeak of him in their Lamentation to this day.</hi> So that we
may conclude thus much from that Hiſtory, that when <hi>Joſiah</hi> was
ſlain, there was in <hi>Iſrael</hi> an Act, an Ordinance, a Law made for a
ſolemn yearly Mourning for ever.</p>
            <p>We ſee then, we are now aſſembled by a Law made after a
Precedent of great Antiquity, and I may add, of much greater Authority. And
ſince Providence has for our Sins given us the like Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, let us
implore his merciful Acceptance of the like Mourning and Humiliation; and of
our Service and Sorrow in Obedience to the Law in our own Nation, made after
the example of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and of this Divine Ordinance, wherein the
Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven was moſt immediately concern'd.</p>
            <p>The Civil Magiſtrate may, by what Rules he pleaſes, enquire
after Perſons diſaffected, and uneaſy to the Government; but methinks it
were very natural to ſuſpect all ſuch perſons as dangerous to Kings and
States, who rejoyce and ſeem to triumph at the fall of one of the beſt of
Kings; and at the promotion of the worſt of Men and Murderers into his place.
It cannot be ſafe laughing, when a Nation, upon ſo good reaſon, is
commanded to be all in Tears; not only leſt God ſhould be angry, whoſe
Judgments are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deſpiſed; but alſo leſt that Man who can be
merry upon ſo ſad, and lamentable an occaſion,<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97331:4"/>ſhould
be thought pleas'd with the publick Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and that common Calamity which was
the cauſe of it.</p>
            <p>Every Man's experience tells him thus much, that what we are glad
of, we wiſh may happen frequently; and that occaſion and matter of Joy can
never come too often: ſo that ſhould the Anniverſary for one Prince's
Murder be to any Man a day of Joy, I ſhould ſuſpect that Man wiſhes
more ſuch days as theſe; and that we may have many ſuch reaſons for
<hi>Jeremy</hi> to lament.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, what a Man ſorrows, and grieves, and mourns
for, he wiſhes may never be repeated; and that he may never hear of the like
again. So that days of Humiliation (as they have ſometimes been ſerviceable
to Hypocriſie) may ſerve for Politick Ends and Purpoſes, as well as
Religious; to ſecure Princes from all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of cruel and bloody Men, by
creating an averſion to ſuch barbarous Practices upon them, in the minds of
all Men.</p>
            <p>It is very natural for Sorrow and Shame to fill the Mind with
horror and diſlike of all Events or Actions which cauſed ſorrow; to
poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the Mind with a principle and habitual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to prevent
ſuch Actions for the time to come; and all the Efforts and Endeavours which
are made towards them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> had therefore very good reaſon to 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97331:4"/>make an Ordinance for a yearly Mourning for
<hi>Joſiah,</hi> as all other States and Governments have upon the like
occaſion; becauſe ſorrow and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction for the untimely Death of one
King, diſpoſes the Mind to Care and Vigilance over the Life and Welfare of
another. And I think common Charity will teach us to believe, That he who now
does his dury to God, and is juſt to the Bleſſed Memory of this day's
Martyr, can do no injury to the State or Perſon of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
Succeſſor; nor give way to ſo much as a Thought which may prejudice the
Intereſt of that Brave Man, who through ſo many Perils, has aſſerted
the Religion and Honour of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>We may reckon upon Two ſorts of Men who are avowed Enemies to
our preſent Conſtitution: The <hi>Firſt</hi> are thoſe little Wretches,
who yet dare meditate great and Bloody Villanies; and endeavour the Confuſion
of their own Native Country, by Aſſaſſines, and bringing in upon us a
Foreign Power. Theſe are not to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, becauſe little; ſince it
has often been in the power of Wretches, and ſmall things, to do great
miſchiefs. But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There are other Enemies who are far more
powerfull, and who have hit upon the only ſtratagem in the World which can
undo us: Such are they who endeavour to make God<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97331:5"/>our Enemy;
and to rob us of his Care and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to whom alone we owe our Protection and
Peace. When the Almighty thunders, and when his Judgments are abroad, he
expects we ſhould tremble and be afraid; and not live as if we ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther defid
Heaven, and God, and Providence; or did not believe them: Now the taking away
the moſt Pious and beſt of Kings, by the moſt impious and inhumane
Practices, and by a Civil War; where Subject was againſt Sovereign, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
againſt Son, the Bonds of Affection, Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Blood and Nature, all
diſſolv'd, and Hell broke looſe, was certainly a very dreadfull Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of God upon a People, tho' it were no worſe; and if we be not ſenſible of
it, God can make us know and underſtand it to our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, (which Heaven
forbid!) by bringing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us again the like Calamity. I ſay, the
Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations which attended the downfall of God's Anointed, will bear
Witneſs, that God was very Angry; and it is but modeſty in duſt and
aſhes to humble our ſelves under the ſence of his diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>I do not now conſider the Death of King <hi>Charles,</hi> as a
Sin, much leſs as a Murder, and a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Murder, the moſt crying of all
Sins. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he had only fallen as <hi>Joſiah</hi> did by a chance Arrow
from a Bow; or by a Ball or Dart, which reſpects no Perſons, nor has
ſence to diſtinguiſh<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97331:5"/>betwixt right and wrong; yet were
it for no other reaſon, but becauſe his Death was one of God's Judgments,
which are all terrible; and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting from the Sin and Crime that lie
heavy upon this Nation; we have ſtill reaſon, as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> and
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had, to lament; and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our Mourning, as well as
the Memory of God's Anger and Indignation.</p>
            <p>Think then who are they that feaſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce; that make this
a Day of Paſtime and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, which the Almighty made a day of Vengeance;
which the Church has ſet a part for a day of Mourning; which the Law has
appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a ſolemn Faſt: think again, who are they that provoke God to
anger, by deſpiſing theſe his Judgments, and ridiculing the Signs and
To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of his heavy Diſpleaſure; and then ſee if theſe be not the
Enemies we are moſt in danger of. Theſe are the Men who are to make God our
Enemy; and when they have done that, it is in vain they boaſt of their
Fidelity, and of their other Services to this or any Eſtabliſhment. They
are better men, and better friends to this their Country, who arm Ruffians;
then they who arm God and Heaven and Providence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us; and who put the
Sword into the Hand of the deſtroying Angel to undo us. Other Foes may have
as much Malice; but cannot do half the Miſchief, as they who defy God and his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97331:6"/>Ordinances, are able to do. We fear the ſecret Contrivances
and Conſpiracies of ill Men at home; we are providing againſt the
Aſſaults of a crazy Mortal from abroad, and of Forces which could not till
this Day have ſtood before us, but as our Sins and our Follies had given them
advantage over us, and kept them up: but there's no fencing nor fighting
againſt Heaven; if our open defiance of God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments provoke Him to
puniſh, or to forſake us.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ſhewn that the taking away a good King, though
conſider'd only as God's Judgment upon a People, and not their Crime, yet
ought to be remember'd with the laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degree of Humiliation; and looked
upon as a Sign that God was diſpleaſed with that Land, which he made the
Theatre whereon was ſhed ſo much Innocent Blood. No man ſin'd when
<hi>Joſiah</hi> was ſlain in Battle; yet the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God and the
Nation (only becauſe he was kill'd in the Field) made a Law for a yearly
Mourning for Him, through all future Ages.</p>
            <p>I now come to Two particular Reaſons which I find in the
Hiſtory of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> why the people made ſo great, and ſo
univerſal Lamentation for Him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> A Prince was ſlain in Battle, whoſe
Clemency, and Goodneſs; and whoſe Zeal for<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97331:6"/>Religion, had
created Him a general Eſteem and Veneration among all his People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> had reaſon to mourn, and to
be afflicted, when he dyed; becauſe it was propheſied, that the Calamity of
that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould commence and bear date from the very day
<hi>Joſiah</hi> ſhould be taken from them.<note place="margin">2
<hi>Chron.</hi> 34.24,28.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Firſt Reaſon why the <hi>Jews</hi> made
ſo great Mourning for <hi>Joſiah,</hi> was, becauſe his Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and
Goodneſs, and his great Piety had got him a general Eſteem and Veneration
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his People. <hi>Now the reſt of the acts of</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, <hi>and
his Goodneſs,</hi> or Clemency and Kindneſs, <hi>according to all that is
written in the Law of the Lord, behold they are in the Book of the
Kings of Iſrael and Judah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi>
35.26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Here is then an Argument for the Peoples Mourning, and for an
Ordinance to eſtabliſh a yearly Mourning; becauſe Violence had taken from
them not only a great Prince, but alſo a very good Man: his Clemency became
his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and his Goodneſs or his Graces ſhone brighter than all the
Jewels in his Crown. He was Religiouſly Good; he was Good out of Principle
and Conſcience, and not only out of Policy, and in appearance; his
Goodneſs, or, as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> reads it, his Clemency and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
would endure the Touchſtone; for, <hi>it was according to the Law of the
Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97331:7"/>Now this is the true Standard for all Virtue,
and he who can walk according to this Rule, is a perfect Man. This is a Law
that is fit to be the Study and Care of Princes; becauſe by it they not only
hold their Crown and Dignity on Earth, but alſo hope for a more laſting
Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Crown in Heaven. No wonder then if goodneſs win upon the
Hearts and Affections of all the World; for moſt Men are in love with Vertue,
though few will practiſe it.</p>
            <p>And therefore a greater thing cannot be ſaid of any Man, nor of
any King or Prince of the Sons of Men, than that he's good according to God's
Law: other Excellencies may make a Man great in Imagination, and continue his
Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory ſo long as Marble will bear his Name; but it is his Goodneſs, and
this only, that gives him Immortality, and a Name and Honour, that will endure
for ever.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory tells us, That <hi>Joſiah</hi> came very young to
the Throne; <hi>That he was but Eight Years old when he began to
reign.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.1.</note> He muſt needs at
that Age want Underſtanding; and Wiſdom, and Experience, and Strength to
wield the Scepter of that Kingdom; and <hi>Solomon</hi> denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>Wo to
that Land, whoſe King is a Child.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi>
10.16.</note> But <hi>Joſiah</hi> made up all theſe Deficiencies, and
Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections in Nature, by the early ſupplies of Divine Goodneſs, and of
Grace. 
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.2.</note> During our 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97331:7"/>Minority we are under Tutelage and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of others we
ſuppoſe, wiſer then our ſelves; and Honeſt as well as able to direct
and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage our Affairs; who yet have many failings, at the very beſt; and
great allowances muſt be made even for their Infirmities: But this young
Prince choſe for the Guide and Conduct of his Infancy, <hi>the Ancient of
Days;</hi> and of him to learn Experience, who himſelf knew all things by
Intuition, and at the firſt ſight. Here we have a Guardian who can defend
his Charge, and protect his Orphan, againſt the Invaſions and Incroachments
of his greedy Neighbour: Here is a Counſellor who knows the ſtate of
Nations, and ſees into all affairs of Princes both Foreign and at Home: He
knows what's done in this Cabal, in that Cabinet, in the other Conclave; nay.
He knows the Hearts, and underſtands our Thoughts long before. So that a
Child, and Infant of a King, under His Conduct, ſhall undermine the
Counſels of <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> That he choſe <hi>David</hi>
for his Pattern, whom he would imitate, without going aſide to the right or
left hand. Now <hi>David</hi> was a glorious Precedent for any Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on
Earth to take Example by: He was great in Arms, and in Religion; admired for
Courage, and for Devotion: and (to ſatisfie<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97331:8"/>all the World,
that Religion does not make Cowards) He was therefore Great in the Field,
becauſe Devout at the Altar, and in the Houſe of God.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not give any account of the many eminent Vertues either
of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> or the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr;</hi> thoſe of the latter which were
moſt in View and in Exerciſe, were Patience and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance; and it is
but Melancholy diſcourſing on theſe Vertues, as well as practiſing
them. They were both of them Zealous for Religion, and for Reforming to the
True, Ancient and Primitive Way; They both ſtudied to adorn the Temple, and
to ſerve God in the Beauty of Holineſs: It was their Endeavour to cleanſe
the Houſe of God from Sordidneſs and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; and to
diſtinguiſh it from a Gaol, or a Den of Thieves: And if others had but been
as Careful to have ſerved Them, as they were Active and Induſtrious to
ſerve their God; they might have had a much more proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and longer
Reign, over a far better and far more happy People.</p>
            <p>And yet it is not to be wonder'd at, That ſo much Vertue and
Piety, that ſo pure a Zeal for Religion and the Love of God, ſhould
ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time happen to be utterly over-run and ruin'd by the groſſeſt
Atheiſm and Hypocriſie, that ever paſs'd upon Mankind. Our
<hi>Joſiah</hi> was<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97331:8"/>bound up to the ſtricteſt Honour,
Truth, and Juſtice; and could do nothing which might be a blemiſh to any of
theſe, though it were to ſave a Kingdom: when as his Enemies were for
Liberty; and (as their practice explain'd it) were to be confin'd to no Rule or
Principle; were to be bound by no Law or Promiſe, but to act purely, and
entirely, as their Intereſt ſhould direct.</p>
            <p>If a Man make a Conſcience of Truth and Juſtice, then Liberty
of Conſcience is very good, and men ſeldom want it: but where there is no
Conſcience, all Men muſt own, that Liberty is very dangerous; it then
becomes Licentiouſneſs, or a Liberty, ſuch as our Martyr's Enemies made
their own, and which was allow'd to none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, to kill, and to take
Poſſeſſion; and to wade through the blood of Innocents, to every thing
they imagined would enrich, honour, or advance them.</p>
            <p>And thus I have done with my <hi>firſt</hi> Reaſon, why ſo
great Lamentation for <hi>Joſiah.</hi> He was Religiouſly good; and the
loſs of ſuch a Prince is hardly to be repaired.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> had reaſon to mourn, when
<hi>Joſiah</hi> dyed; becauſe it was propheſy'd to them, That their
Calamity and Miſery ſhould commence from the very day that
<hi>Joſiah</hi> ſhould be taken away from them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97331:9"/>It was told them by <hi>Huldah</hi> the
Propheteſs, That God was very angry with that people, and that he had
dreadfull Judgments in Reſerve. whereby to puniſh the Obſtinacy of the
<hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation: but that for <hi>Joſiah's</hi> ſake, that moſt
pious and moſt religious Prince, he would not execute his Vengeance ſo long
as he ſhould live; but would defer his Indignation till that great, good Man
ſhould be carry'd to his Grave in Peace: that then, and from that time,
<hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould be a miſerable and an afflicted People; and a
hiſſing and an aſtoniſhment to all Nations round about them.</p>
            <p>According to this Decree revealed to, and foretold them by the
Propheteſs, all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell them: <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Sons and
Succeſſors were one of them carry'd away by <hi>Necho</hi> King of
<hi>Egypt;</hi> another was depoſed by the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi> a third
was taken Priſoner, and judgment given againſt Him; his Sons all ſlain
before his Eyes, and then his Eyes bored out, that he might ſee no more of
the Miſery which he was to ſuffer. Now ſince this was all foretold them,
and that all their temporal Bliſs and Happineſs depended upon the Thred of
<hi>Joſiah's</hi> life, no wonder they made great Lamentation when he
dyed.</p>
            <p>The Ancients reported, that in <hi>Troy</hi> there was an Image,
which they believed fell from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which ſo long as they could preſerve
ſafe<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97331:9"/>within their Walls, would preſerve them
ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full againſt all Enemies from abroad; but the loſs of it was to
foretell the Ruin of their City and Civil Government. King <hi>Joſiah</hi>
was this Image, and gave the ſame ſecurity to <hi>Judah</hi> and
<hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> and they were well aſſured, that whilſt this
<hi>Palladium</hi> was among them, no Injury could befall them either from
Heaven or Earth; for he who is Lord of both, had given his Word for it.</p>
            <p>He therefore falling in <hi>Megiddo,</hi> cauſed this
Lamentation among the People; their Peace, their Plenty, their Laws, Religion
and Lives were all in Danger when he was in Peril, or in the leaſt
Diſtreſs; all their Glory was caſt down when he fell in Battle; and the
Arrow that wounded him, went to the Heart of every good Man in his
Dominions.</p>
            <p>This is therefore my ſecond Reaſon for ſo great Mourning in
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> at that time.</p>
            <p>Now give me leave to apply theſe Reaſons of <hi>Judah</hi> and
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s Lamentation for their King, who fell in Battle, and was
ſlain in the Valley or Plain of <hi>Megiddo.</hi> There was upon it an
Ordinance, a Law made for a ſolemn Mourning; and it was obſerved even after
the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Monarchy was deſtroy'd. I hope our Law of the ſame
nature, made after that Divine Example, and ordained for the ſame end and 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97331:10"/>purpoſe, may long continue together with the Enghſh
Monarchy; and even for that very end, that the Monarchy may long endure. The
<hi>Jews</hi> Mourning for <hi>Joſiah</hi> endured longer then their Kingdom.
Their yearly Faſt for <hi>Gedaliah,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their
Diſperſion, is religiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by them to this day; and although
they are broken and ſcattered abroad in all Nations, and among all Languages;
yet their Lamentation is continued with one Voice, and one Conſent.</p>
            <p>It were not hard to make it appear, That we have as great Reaſon
to continue our Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the <hi>Jews</hi> had for <hi>Joſiah:</hi>
and, may be, it were happy for us if we had not other, and greater Reaſons
for this day's Solemnity, then the <hi>Jews</hi> had. <hi>Joſiah</hi> was
ſlain by a foreign Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: He fell in Battle, and was killed in the heat of
Blood; Himſelf was in a Diſguiſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known; and an Arrow ſhot at
Random, wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Him that He dyed: His own People were no way guilty; His Death
could not be charged upon any of them; nor was their Land put under a Curſe,
or defiled with Innocent Blood. Let the Armies of <hi>Egypt</hi> and
<hi>Pharaoh Necho</hi> anſwer for it: <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi>
had no hand in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſiah</hi> was not murder'd by His own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, nor
try'd, condemn'd, and executed by<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97331:10"/>Men whom he had patronis'd
and promoted to Wealth and Honour: <hi>Joſiah</hi> was not brought to the Bar
or Scaffold, by Men who fought againſt his Perſon by his own
Commiſſion; nor did he die by the hand of Thieves and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, who, when
they had ſlain the Heir, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded among them the Inheritance.
<hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were all of them of another Countrey, and had
never vow'd Duty, nor ſworn Allegiance to him: and ſuch Men may have, by
the Laws of Nature and Nations, a greater Liberty to invade and make War, then
Men born and educated in his own Dominions.</p>
            <p>But then, If the King of <hi>Judah,</hi> only fallen in Battle,
and ſlain by a foreign Enemy, cauſed ſo general Lamentation, and ſuch
as was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued through the Reigns of all the ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kings, till the
<hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity; and which was obſerved even in the time of
<hi>Cyrus,</hi> and the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchy; (as the laſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of
2 <hi>Chron.</hi> does ſufficiently evince:) How much greater, and more
laſting Humiliation ſhould Ours be, who have the Guilt of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood
at our own Doors? A Prince, who was Himſelf all Pity and Compaſſion,
ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and put to Death by cruel and bloody Men; a King who had been a
kind Father to his People, worry'd and devour'd by his own Children! here is
Guilt that may demand Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97331:11"/>till the Day of
Judgment.</p>
            <p>The Almighty has ever declared to the World, That the Blood of the
pooreſt Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent defiles the Land; and that whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Countries
have a long time lain under the Curſe and Cry of it. Ancient Wiſe Men
fill'd their Tragedies, and loaded their Scenes with God's Judgments upon
Murder; Theatres groaned under the weight of publick Guilt; and Towns and
Cities felt the Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, eſpecially upon the Effuſion of Royal Blood,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Lord,</hi> (ſays
<hi>Oedipus</hi> in <hi>Sophocles</hi>) <hi>What a ſtorm of Vengeance falls
upon our City for this King's Blood?</hi> The very Heathen Gods ſeem not to
have been at reſt, till the Blood of Innocents was atoned for, or revenged;
and the Saints in Heaven, and Souls of Martyrs now with God, though them
ſelves all flaming Charity and Love to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, yet call for Vengeance upon
the Earth, for the Innocent Blood that has been ſhed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. <hi>And I
ſaw</hi> (ſays S. <hi>John,</hi>)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi>
6.9,10.</note> 
               <hi>under the Altar, the Souls of them that were ſlain for the
Word of God.—And they cryed with a loud Voice, ſaying, How long, O
Lord, holy, and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our blood on them that
dwell on the Earth?</hi> So that in Caſe of Blood, even Mercy it ſelf turns
cruel, and calls for Juſtice, and cannot reſt till it be reveng'd.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97331:11"/>And now, whether we believe <hi>Moſes</hi>
or S. <hi>John,</hi> or even <hi>Sophocles</hi> the Tragedian; They all with
one Voice conclude, That a Drop of Innocent Blood is enough to bring a Deluge
of Miſery upon a Nation.</p>
            <p>But who will deny, That Innocent Blood was ſhed as on This Day,
and in This Land; and not only the Blood of a Man, who had done no harm; but
under whom we might have enjoy'd both Wealth and Honour; who nouriſhed Arts,
encouraged Learning, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Religion, maintain'd the Peoples Liberties,
pardon'd great Offenders; and at laſt was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd, and put to Death, by
many of thoſe who had been forgiven by him.</p>
            <p>All Nations have owned, That Kings are Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their Countrey;
and the Voice of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliz'd and Learned Nations, is the Voice of Nature and of
God. Now for a Man to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own Father, is of all ſins of the worſt
kind, the very worſt, and moſt clamorous, and cries loudeſt to Heaven for
Vengeance.</p>
            <p>In ſhort then, The People had no ſin to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for, when
<hi>Joſiah</hi> died; and yet they had Mourning by an Ordinance, and by a
Law: but in our caſe, the People of This Nation ſlew their own Prince, and
had their Hands dyed in the Blood of their Sovereign; of Him, who by Birth,
Title, Poſſeſſion, Care, Kindneſs,<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97331:12"/>Courteſie,
and every thing that could either give or purchaſe Right, was Father of his
Countrey.</p>
            <p>It is not very difficult to diſcern how the Almighty has ever
ſince chaſtiſed and ſcourged This Nation; and how that horrid Murder,
and Effuſion of Sacred Blood, has been the Cauſe of many publick Calamities
This Land has ſince groaned under. His Death was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with the Blood
of Thouſands, other great Men; and He went to Heaven with a royal Army of
Martyrs to attend upon Him. Then it was, That Men's Honeſty was their Crime,
and Wealth and good Eſtates were to others as bad as Felony. It were
endleſs to reckon up, how many brave Men were oblig'd to fly for their Lives;
to pray for Sanctuary, and Protection in a Foreign Land; to take Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in
another Nation, thereby to eſcape a moſt wretched Bondage and Captivity in
their own Countrey.</p>
            <p>We have been ever ſince (and may be not without Reaſon) under
Fears and Jealouſies of a Foreign Religion; even the Bleſſings and Sweets
of the Reſtauration, were made bitter to us, by the Wormwood and Gall of
Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition infuſed into our Cup; and by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours which have been
uſed to bring our Souls into Bondage. Only the Wiſdom and 
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97331:12"/>Goodneſs of Heaven in this mighty Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we hope,
may free us from thoſe Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of Superſtition coming in among us,
the Equivocal Offspring of that otherwiſe happy Reſtauration. But ſtill
we muſt remember who firſt drove thoſe Kings into a Countrey, where they
might be taught Superſtition; and that if they had not when young, been
purſued out of their own Land, they would not have been tempted by the Gods
of other Kingdoms: if they had been Educated under their own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in their
own Countrey, under their own Laws, and ſuffered to breath their own Native
Air, they might have been zealous Patrons of the Religion and Intereſt of
their own Nation; and the Miſeries we have laboured under, upon that account,
will, in a good meaſure, lye at the doors of thoſe, who drove them out of
the Church, into the Idols Temple.</p>
            <p>And having thus far aſſign'd, and apply'd the Reaſons of
<hi>Judah</hi>'s Lamentation; give me leave to ſum up what other things I
have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven with this Diſcourſe. I have ſhewn,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the downfall of that good King, whom we now
lament, taking all the Miſeries that did belong to it, from firſt to
laſt, was a moſt viſible mark of God's Diſpleaſure; and, may be, ſo
ſevere a Judgment as this Land ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver felt, ſince it was a Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97331:13"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That God's Judgments upon a
People ought not to be neglected; much leſs, to be made our Paſtime, and
entertain'd with Raillery and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>God
ſcorns the ſcorners, and that He will laugh when their Fear
cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the Peoples ſhedding the Blood of their
Soveraign, was a Publick Crime, as well as a Publick Judgment and Calamity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That although the Effuſion of his Innocent
Blood were no more then a private or a perſonal Crime, or the Sin only of
thoſe Men who acted in it; yet the puniſhment is Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, and the Land
polluted. The Nation is one Body Politick, and the whole muſt anſwer for
what one or a few Members have done amiſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That the Pollution of the Land with Blood,
ſubmits the Nation to the Curſe of God, which he has ſaid he will
ſometimes continue to the third or fourth Generation; and the <hi>Jews</hi>
when they were ſo vehement for our Lord's dying as a Malefactor, took his
Blood upon themſelves and their Poſterity.</p>
            <p>I come now to the laſt thing I am to ſpeak to, and that
is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That He upon whom God's Judgment falls, is not
always the Perſon who offended, but the Innocent are many times the
Sufferers, when the Guilty eſcape, and go free. <hi>Joſiah</hi> 
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97331:13"/>loſt his Crown and Life; but it is, <hi>Wo to us, for we
have ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Kings have often ſuffered for the Sins of the People; and
perhaps as often has an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Nation been ſcourged and plagued for the
Sins of their King. For <hi>Firſt, David</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber'd the People, which was
not their fault; nor was it in their Power to prevent their being reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd up,
if the Prince of the People would have it ſo: But the Plague fell upon them
alone, and not upon the Perſon who had done the Offence. <hi>David</hi> owns
thus much in the Preſence of God and the Congregation: <hi>It is I that have
ſinned, Lord, what have theſe ſilly ſheep done? Secondly,</hi> the Son
of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> dy'd young, or was by God removed out of the way by Death;
not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe He had offended, but becauſe He ſhould not ſee the Evil
which was to fall upon his Friends and Countrevmen who had. <hi>He only of all
the Houſe of Jeroboam ſhall go to the Grave in Peace, becauſe in him was
found ſome good.</hi> His good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhorten'd his days; He was early ripe
for Heaven and for Eternity, as the reſt of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily were for
deſtruction: Yet this young Prince did not loſe a Crown, which he might
have come to by ſlow ways of Succeſſion and of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; but was
haſten'd and tranſlated to a Crown that is Immortal.</p>
            <p>This young Son of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> it is ſaid, went 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97331:14"/>down to the Grave in Peace. I would here ſtop a little to
enquire what is meant by a Man's going to the Grave in Peace. Is it to live as
long as the Courſe of Nature will allow? Is it to wear well for Threeſcore
Years and Ten, and then to dye an eaſy and a Natural Death? and the Lamp of
Life to go out purely for want of Oil? No, far otherwiſe. It is ſaid of
<hi>Joſiah,</hi> that He ſhould go to the Grave in Peace. <hi>Behold I will
gather Thee to thy Fathers, and Thou ſhalt be gathered to thy Grave in
Peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 34.28.</note> Now I have already
ſhewn, That <hi>Joſiah</hi> was mortally wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Megiddo,</hi> and
fell in Battle: and how can ſuch a Man who is defeated, and dyes in War, be
ſaid to go to the Grave in Peace? And yet <hi>Joſiah</hi> who fell by the
Hand of an <hi>Egyptian;</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> Son, who was cut off by
Death in the moſt flouriſhing ſtate of life: I ſay they both went to
the Grave in Peace.</p>
            <p>Now to dye, or go to the Grave in Peace, does not reſpect the
kinds of Death, whether in Battle or on a Scaffold, or of old Age, and in a
Man's Bed: but it regards the Perſon who dyes; and that Temper and
Chearfulneſs and quiet of Mind wherein a man dyes. He then dyes in Peace,
whom Outrages and Indignities can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not provoke to Anger; and whoſe Patience
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remains unſhaken, when the Storms and Waves of Sorrow beat hardeſt upon
Him. He dyes in<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97331:14"/>Peace, who reſigns his own Will to the
Will and Pleaſure of him who made him; and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the moſt painful or
ſhameful way of Dying, as the ready way to Immortality and Eternal Life: Thus
dyed <hi>Joſiah,</hi> though he fell in Battle; and thus fell the Royal
Martyr, though Murder'd in the face of the Sun, and his own Subjects. How he
went to the Grave, it is not known; the Graves of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of King
<hi>Charles</hi> being concealed by the Will of God to this day.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, there's one Reaſon why Martyrs ſhould not ſo
much be ſaid to die in Peace, as they who die in Battle, or in their Bed;
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe tho' they go out of the World with a calm and quiet Mind, yet their
Blood calling for Vengeance, ſeems to declare War: But in all other
reſpects, Men who die for Religion, and patiently ſuffer in a good Cauſe,
though ſawn aſunder, or torn with wild Horſes, and devour'd by Birds or
Beaſts of the Field, may very well be ſaid to go to the Grave in Peace.</p>
            <p>It is very true, that Sorrow, and Suffering, and Death, did all
come into the World to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and were occaſioned by the ſin of Man; and
are all of them continued as Scourges and Judgments of God upon Man for ſin.
The Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty has but one Arrow in his Quiver ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97331:15"/>than theſe; and that he ſends among us, when he puniſhes ſin
with ſin; when he ſuffers ill Men to harden in Impenitence, to encreaſe
their Guilt, and thereby conſigns them over to Damnation. This is the moſt
dreadful, and amazing Judgment of God upon Earth, to leave a Man to a reprobate
ſence, and hard heart, and on this ſide the Grave and Hell, without all
hopes of Redemption.</p>
            <p>I know not but there may be Men in the World, thus left to
themſelves; who inſtead of repenting of a moſt horrid Murder, and of
ſhedding Innocent Blood, have themſelves and their Poſterity, juſtified
the doing it, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced from the Blood of one King, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the
Lawfulneſs of reſiſting all Kings. To ſin, is not ſo great a fault,
as to vindicate and maintain the lawfulneſs of committing Sin; we are all
ſinners, but hope God will give us Grace to repent and amend; and then we are
again right in his ſight: But to ſhed Innocent Blood, and to juſtify the
doing it, is what Highway-men, and common Thieves and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers will not do.</p>
            <p>Now Reſiſting is a comprehenſive Word, and includes in it
reviling and ſtandering, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and putting to Death; and that, what way
you pleaſe, whether by Ponyard or Piſtol,<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97331:15"/>on an open
Theatre, or by Aſſaſſines in the High-Way. Any, or all of theſe are
Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to as many as believe it Lawful to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
            <p>Do but then think, Who are they that have been plotting againſt
the Lord's Anointed? Who have been engaged in Conſpiracies to murder him in
ſecret, and by ſurpriſe? Who have been in Conſult and Intriguing with a
Foreign Enemy to invade us; and upon what bottom all this mighty proceſs has
been form'd and founded, but upon this helliſh Principle, That it is Lawful
to reſiſt. Our Prince is hereby in as much danger in his Palace, or in his
Bed, as formerly in a Battle; and his very Recreations may be as perilous, as
when he ſtorms a Caſtle, or takes a Town. We have heard of theſe mens
Crimes, and ſometimes of their Abſolution, but not a word of any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Repentance for publick Sins; but all go out of the World with a quiet Mind, or
are only ſorry their Attempts ſucceeded not. Now this can proceed from no
other Cauſe, but from that ſole Principle and Opinion, That it is Lawful to
reſiſt; and to embrew their Hands in that Sacred Blood, which has been too
fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, and too far expoſed in our Defence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97331:16"/>I wiſh that ſort of Men would deal fairly;
and inſtead of vending among the People thoſe Jeſuitical Notions and
Speculations, they would go directly to the Prince's Chambers, and tell them
Him, and give Him timely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to look to Himſelf; for that they will
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell when they pleaſe, and themſelves are the proper Judges of their own
time.</p>
            <p>This is the real truth of the matter; and Men who juſtifie
Reſiſtance, and intend to practiſe it, do not intend to ask the King's
leave when they go about it; do not wait for an Order of Council, or a Patent
or Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under the Broad Seal; but their Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience is their
Commiſſion, and they bear their Authority on their Sword's point.</p>
            <p>Thus, I ſay, God has given ſome Men over to a reprobate Sence,
and from Murdering one King, to maintain, That all others may be lawfully
Murder'd. This is ſurely the moſt direful Curſe, that ever happen'd to
any People, to be given over to Impenitence and a hard Heart; a Man in this
ſtate, is got within the confines of Hell, even while he lives upon Earth,
and has gone ſo far within the Gulph, that he cannot return.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was once angry, and he repented. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
was guilty of Murder and Adultery, and<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97331:16"/>with Tears he
waſhed off the guilt of Blood, and of Uncleanneſs. S. <hi>Peter</hi> deny'd
his Lord, and wept bitterly: Nay, <hi>Judas</hi> made ſome ſort of
Confeſſion, and ſeemed to be ſorry, when he returned the Money which
was the Price of Blood: <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf never betray'd and
reſiſted, and taught others to reſiſt: ſo that this is one degree
above his Crime, and will be puniſhed in a place below him.</p>
            <p>Men of no Religion, and who have written in behalf of a Liberty, I
had almoſt ſaid, in behalf of an Indifferency of all Religions; yet have
thought fit to own, That Principles not conſiſtent with the repoſe, and
quiet, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Government, ought not to be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated or endured.
Now Men who teach and juſtifie the Lawfulneſs of reſiſting Kings,
main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all Principles of Confuſion, in one word.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> It will be hard to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
Reſiſtance and Rebellion; they are Twins, ſo very like each other, that
without ſome nicety in Metaphyſicks, a Man would miſtake them for one and
the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If a Man may Lawfully reſiſt, no man can
Lawfully hinder Him, or put a ſtop to his Reſiſtance: for what has any
man to do to hinder or moleſt me, when I am doing a Lawful thing? I am then
about my Lawful Employment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97331:17"/>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If Reſiſtance be
lawfull, and men do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lawfull Actions, are not to be hindered or moleſted;
be ſure upon that account they cannot lawfully be puniſhed: and then all
Treaſons may go on and proſper.</p>
            <p>And now as we are bound to pray for Kings and all in Authority;
ſo it is no leſs our Duty to teach ſuch Doctrines as may ſecure to them
the Poſſeſſion of that Power and Soveraignty they have over us, and the
Duty and Allegeance we owe them as God's Miniſters for our good. It is not
Affection alone, nor is it Principle alone, that renders Kings ſafe in the
Enjoyment of their Crown and Dignity: Principle may be too weak, when Affection
is loſt and gone; and Affection for a Prince without Principle too, is but
mutable and uncertain; our Love is apt to vary and change; and Affection goes
with Intereſt, and turns with it; but when Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for a Prince, and a
Principle of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience are joyn'd and united, they make a Bond that will
hold a <hi>Sampſon,</hi> and which the ſtrongeſt Man cannot break.</p>
            <p>But to conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Our Law and our publick Prayers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of a
Murder committed as on This Day, and of the ſhedding Royal Blood: Let us
mourn and ſorrow for it, though as to our ſelves we had no 
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97331:17"/>hand in it, (the Heart muſt grieve for what the hand
does) and thereby we ſhall teſtify to all the World, That although there is
upon our Land the Guilt of Blood; yet we are not thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages that delight
in Blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> God in his Juſtice took away
<hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah;</hi> and He frequently takes away good Kings, when the ſins of
the People tempt and provoke Him to it; He has hitherto been gracious to us,
and deliver'd our Soveraign both from hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Conſpiracies, and open
Violence; and has been his Defence, when thouſands have fallen at his Right
and Left Hand. Let us not by our Sins tempt God to take from us that
Bleſſing we enjoy in Him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> had their Temple and City
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> deſtroy'd, and themſelves carried away Captive, after
the Death of <hi>Joſiah:</hi> think you they were Sinners above others? I
tell you nay. The ſame People of God the <hi>Jews</hi> for the Murder of our
Saviour, were above Forty years afterwards finally ruin'd, they and their
Children: think ye they were Sinners above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? I tell you nay. We know
what follows.</p>
            <p>Here is likewiſe the Cry of Innocent Blood at this day; and we
cannot preſume that we have yet ſhed Tears enough to waſh off the ſtain
and pollution from our Land; but that Poſterity<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97331:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>and
Childrens Children may mourn under the Curſe and Cry of it. <hi>Wo to
us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is a proper Subject for <hi>Jeremy</hi>'s Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; here
a man might (with Him) wiſh his Head a Well of Water, and his Eyes a
Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Tears, to bewail the Miſeries due to ſo ſinfull, ſo
ungodly, ſo ungovernable a People. <hi>Remember, O Lord, and let not thoſe
things come upon us which our ſins deſerve. Let not our Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance be
turned to ſtrangers, nor our Houſes to Aliens who would be Lords over us.
Spare us, good Lord! Spare thy People! turn away thy Wrath from us, and
together with all our other Iniquities pardon the Sin of this day, Thou who
haſt ſhed thine own Blood to ſave us from Sin and from Wrath to
come.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
